A Guide to the Population Council records, John D. Rockefeller 3rd Dockets, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 10 FA1430
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, John D. Rockefeller 3rd Dockets, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 10
1962-1972
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison), 1906-1978
FA1430
2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter-size document boxes.
Arrangement
Primarily chronological by meeting date.
Scope and Contents
This series contains copies of dockets, agendas and meeting materials given to, or prepared for, John D. Rockefeller 3rd and other officers of the Population Council including Donald H. McLean, Jr. and Ray Lamontagne. The records include meetings of the Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, Annual Meeting of the Members, and select conference proceedings and reports.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1962 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1962 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1962 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1963 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd and McLean), 1963 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1963 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1964 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1964 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1964 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1965 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (McLean), 1965 April 21 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (Lamontagne), 1965 October 20 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1965 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (Lamontagne), 1966 April 20 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (Lamontagne), 1966 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Executive Committee Meeting (Lamontagne), 1966 December 21 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1967 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (Lamontagne), 1967 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Executive Committee Meeting (Lamontagne), 1967 December 13 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1968 April 2 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1968 October 16 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Executive Committee Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1968 December 11 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Board of Trustees Meeting, 1969 March 5 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1969 June 4 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1970 March 4 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1970 June 3 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Executive Committee Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1970 September 9 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1970 December 9 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Executive Committee Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1971 March 3 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1971 June 2 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Executive Committee Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1971 September 15 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Annual Meeting of Members and Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1972 June 6 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Executive Committee Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1972 September 13 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Board of Trustees Meeting (JDR 3rd), 1972 December 13 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Studies in Family Planning, with Indexes (JDR 3rd), 1963-1968; 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 35-37)
- Muslim Attitudes toward Family Planning (Lamontagne), 1967 (Box 7, Folder 38)
- Population Papers, Pan American Union (JDR 3rd), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 39)
- Population Papers, Pan American Union (JDR 3rd), La Jolla, CA, 1962 September 9-11 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- Population Projections for San Francisco, 1960-1990 (JDR 3rd), San Francisco Department of City Planning, 1968 April (Box 7, Folder 41)
- Need for Subsidized Family Planning Services: United States, Each State and County 1968, Office of Economic Opportunity, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 42)